Finding Aid for the Book Artifacts Collection, circa 2345 B.C.-1993 A.D. (bulk circa 1510-1976)
The Bancroft Library
- Format, Imposition, Register and Folding, F6
  - Imposition examples: blank sheets, F672, G1-G60
    - Duedecimo, common, cut., F672 G55, No. 2
    - Sextedecimo in two half-sheets worked together in two signatures, F672 G60 No. 1
    - Sextedecimo in one sheet with one signature, F672 G60, No. 2
    - Sextedecimo in two half-sheets worked together, cut and quired, F672 Go 60, No. 3
  - Register, F673
    - Signatures with faculty register, F673, No. 1
  - Signatures, F674
    - [Blank Signatures], F674
  - Folding tools, F678
    - Brown plastic, F678, No. 1
    - Bone, F678, No. 2
- Design, Decoration, and Illustration: Hand Illumination, I4
  During the Middle Age books were written by hand and were produced primarily for the aristocracy and the clergy. Leaves or pages of the books were decorated with gold or silver leaf, which created an illuminated effect. An example of hand illumination in red, blue and gold on vellum leaves from the Book of Hours ca. 1510 is included in the collection.
  - Early printed texts: sample pages, I4A5
    - Book of Hours, France, ca. 1510, I4A5, No. 1
- Design, Decoration, and Illustration: Intaglio and relief processes, I5
  In China woodblocks were used for text and illustration centuries before the development of printing in the West. Most of the Oriental woodblocks in the collection date from the 19th, or possibly the 18th, century. There are prayer boards from Peking, Lhasa, Jehol, and Lama Gagen, a Japanese novel illustration, and the text of an old-style Chinese classical examination.
  In the west early printed books were often illustrated with wood-cuts. Technically described, these of relief prints made from flat-grained wooden block on which the design is cut with the grain by a knife. An Italian block cut in this way to illustrate Vergil’s Aeneid may date from the early 16th century. Modern blocks cut in this way are: Ray Boynton’s fishermen drawing in nets, published in hesperian (Winter issue, 1930) and Walt Whitman’s The World Below the Brine (Berkeley: The Hart Press, 1940); Rich Barton’s pear-wood block for Musical Instruments, a portfolio printed by Henry Evans (San Francisco: The Porpoise Bookshop, 1958); and Valenti Angelo’s “Song of the Rolling Earth,” the only block remaining from the Grabhorn edition of Walt Whitman’s Leaves of Grass (New York: Random House, 1930).
  The art of working with engraving tools such as a burin or graver on the end-grain of dense woods (usually boxwood), a relief technique called wood engraving or white-line engraving, was perfected by Thomas Bewick. He and other 19th century artists working in a similar style are represented by many wood engravings as well as by electrotypes and zinc photoengravings, some of which were made from engravings in the collection. Almost all were once the property of the Merrymount Press in Boston; they came to The Bancroft from Daniel Berkeley Bianchi, whose father was a partner of the proprietor, Daniel Berkeley Updike. The entire gift, some 700 items, was carefully proofed for identification purposes on the Berkeley Albion Press by the fine printer and former printing instructor Roger Levenson. He and the author of the Guide to the collection held a fellowship at the Huntington Library (which owns Updike’s papers and a comprehensive Collection of his publications) to study and identify as many of the artifacts as possible. The results of their work are recorded in volumes 3 and 4 of the BART Register.
  In the early 20th century, the Ashendene Press in England made extensive use of wood engravings, particularly in their famous editions of Dante, Sir Thomas Malory, and Saint Francis of Assisi. A complete collection of the original block for these publications along with Louise Powell’s initial letters for Don Quixote and an engraving of the first home of the press, are the gift of Charlotte and Norman H. Strouse.
  The work of other 20th century artists, notably Thomas Maitland Cleland, Rudolph Ruzicka, and Herman P. Horne, is shown in engravings, electrotypes, and photoengravings from the Merrymount Press. A separate item belonging to an early period in California is Charles Nahl’s celebrated drawing “The Idle Miner’s Death”, as engraved by Thomas Armstrong for publication in Alonzo Delanos The Idle and Industrious Miner (Sacramento: James Armstrong and Co., 1854).
  French wood engravings include a 17th century style book illustration. Renaissance-style initials, and paneled pages, all done in the 19th century.
  Etching, the art of drawing with a need on a treated metal surface and exposing the lines to acid, is shown in three plates, all cancelled, that were designed and etched by Roi Partridge. He also worked in drypoint, which consists in scratching an intaglio design into copper with a pointed steel needle that disturbs the surface, but, unlike the engraver’s burin, does not remove it deeply. In additional to a Partridge drypoint plate, again cancelled, there are plates, both etched and drypoint, for bookplates made early in his career by the writer and art critic Sheldon Cheney. Among them is the copperplate etching for the bookplate of the famous Califorian botanist Willis Linn Jepson.
  Many small press books are illustrated or decorated with linocuts, for example the ornaments Mary Fabilli designed and cut for the Equinox Press of William Everson, also known as Brother Antonious. During the 1950’s Rick Barton, Mark Luca, and Robert Quick did many linocuts for the publications of the Porpoise Bookshop and Peregrine Press of Henry Evans. Two artists in the Evans group, Mel Fowler and Partricia Evans Carpenter, engraved their designs on “Ti-Pi” rubber plates. The amateur printer Frederick Folger Thomas, Jr. used the same medium for decorating his periodical Far Afield.
  - Dealers' catalogs, I5A5
    - Boulevard du Montparnasse, by H. Calmels-paris XIV, I5A5, No. 1
    - Reduced Prices on Tools of Craftsmanship, by Arthur A Crafts & Co., Inc, I5A5, No. 2
    - Diamonds used in Tools, by Arthur A. Crafts & Co., Inc, I5A5, No. 3
    - Price List Catalogue Supplement, by Arthur A. Crafts & Co., Inc., I5A5, No. 4
    - Print Maker's Materials, Graphic Chemical & Ink Co., I5A5, No. 5
    - Printmaker's Materials, by Graphic Chemical Ink & Co., I5A5, No. 6
    - Etching Materials, by Graphic Chemical & Ink Co., I5A5, No. 7
    - Haddon's List of Litho Materials, by John Haddon & Co., I5A5, No. 8
    - Etching and Plate Printing Materials, Tools and C. by John Haddon & Co., I5A5, No. 9
    - 310 Copper plates, by John Haddon & Co., I5A5, No. 10
    - Catalog Number 1 of Etcher's Materials, by Johnson-King Co., I5A5, No. 11
    - Abridged Artist's Nett Price List, by WIlfred C. Kimber, I5A5, No. 12
    - The Etcher's Store, by Wilfred C. Kimber, I5A5, No. 13
    - Price List of Second-Hand Copper Plate Presses, by Wilfred C. Kimber, I5A5, No. 14
    - Arts Decoratifs, by Lefranc, I5A5, No. 15
    - Sierra Brand Copper and Zinc, by Pacific Sheet and Copper Plate Co., I5A5, No. 16
    - Graphic Arts Equipment and Supplies, by Rembrandt Graphic Arts Co., Inc., I5A5, No. 17
    - Graphic Arts Equipment and Supplies, by Rembrandt Graphic Arts Co., Inc., I5A5, No. 18
  - Equipment, I5A6
    - Various Instruments and tools, I5A6, No. 1-27
  - [Miscellaneous supplies for intaglio and relief processes], I5A7
    - Supplies, I5A7, No. 1-11
  - Brass engravings, I5B6
    - Monogram printing plate, I5B6, No. 1
  - Copperplate etchings, U.S., I5C6
    - Blank plates, commercially prepared, I5C6, No. 1-5
    - Etched plate: landscape, unsigned, I5C6, No. 6
    - Trial etching with ground, I5C6, No. 7
    - Plates (chiefly for bookplates) designed and etched by Sheldon Cheney, I5C6 C3, No. 1-14
    - Plates designed and etched by Roi Partridge, I5C6 P2, No. 1-3
  - Copperplate drypoint, U.S., I5C7
    - Plate: head of unidentified woman, designed and executed by Sheldon Cheney, I5C7, No. 1
    - Plate: country scene, designed and executed by Roi Partridge, I5C7, No. 2
  - Copperplate engraving, U.S., I5C8
    - Plate: visiting card, I5C8, No. 1
    - Plate: wedding invitation insertion, I5C8, No. 2
    - Plate: bookplate, designed and engraved by Sheldon Cheney, I5C8, No. 3
  - Linocut blocks, U.S., I5L48
    - Barton, Rick, I5L48 B2, No. 1-94
    - Fabilli, Mary, I5L48 F3, No. 1-18
    - Fowler, Mel, I5L48 F7, No. 1-18
    - Grabhorn Press artist, I5L48 G7, No. 1
    - Hoff, Lloyd, I5L48 H6, No. 1
    - Luca, Mark, I5L48 L8, No. 1-2
    - Quick, Robert, I5L48 Q4, No. 1-5
    - Robertson, Mark, I5L48 R72, No. 1-5
    - Thomas, Fredrick Folger, Jr., I5L48 T5, No. 1-5
    - War Relocation Center artist, I5L48 W4, No. 1-5
  - Rubber engravings, U.S., I5R82
    - Evans, Patricia Healy, I5R82 E8, No. 1-8
    - Fowler, Mel, I5R82 F7, No. 1-13
    - Thomas, Fredrick Folger, Jr., I5R82 T5, No. 1-19
    - Purcell, William Gray, designer; F.F. Thomas, Jr. engraver, I5R82 T5, No. 20-21
    - "Ti-Pi" rubber engraving tools, I5R821, No. 1
  - Steel engravings, European, I5S83
    - Plate: portrait of Joseph Steffens, engraved by John ? of Sheffield, I5S83, No. 1
  - Steel engravings, U.S., 15S88
    - Die: Sutro Library stamp, 15S88, No. 1
    - Monogram printing plate, 15S88, No. 2
    - Dies: Kaiser Company, 15S88, No. 3-10
  - Woodcut blocks, European, I5W66
    - Illustration from Italian Edition of Vergil's Aeneid, I5W66, No. 1
  - Woodcut blocks, Oriental, I5W67
    - Text of Chinese classical examination, 1909, I5W67, No. 1
    - Illustration for Japanese novel, 19th century, I5W67, No. 2
    - Block in Japanese style from Grabhorn shop, I5W67, No. 3
    - Tibetan prayer board from Lama Temple, Peking, I5W67, No. 4
    - Tibetan prayer board from Lhasa, Tibet, I5W67, No. 5
    - Manchurian block used at Jehol for the sacred books of the Lamas, I5W67, No. 6
    - Mongolian prayer board from Lama Gagen, I5W67, No. 7
    - Kim, Hui-jui, I5W67 K6, No. 1
    - Masanobu, Okamura, I5W67 M2, No. 1-2
    - Shigemasa, I5W67 S4, No. 1
  - Woodcut blocks, U.S., I5W68
    - Representation of an angel by an unknown artist, I5W68, No. 1
    - Angelo, Valenti, I5W68 A63, No. 1
    - Barton, Rick, I5W68 B2, No. 1
    - Boynton, Ray, I5W68 B6, No. 1
    - Dean, Mallette, I5W68 D32, No. 1
    - Everson, William, I5W68 E75, No. 1-7
  - Wood engravings, English, I5W73
    - Bewick, Thomas (see also Merrymount Press Collection), I5W73 B38, No. 1-2
    - Catterson-Smith, Robert (Ashendene Dante), I5W73 C22, No. 1-43
    - Gere, Charles (Ashendene Dante, Malory, St. Francis), I5W73 G43, No. 1-40
    - Maynard, R.A. (First Home of the Ashendene Press), I5W73 M26, No. 1
    - Powell, Louise (Initial letters for Ashendene Don Quixote), I5W73 P52, No. 1-9
  - Wood engravings, French, I5W74
    - Paneled pages, Renaissance style, I5W74, No. 1-2
    - Initial letters, Renaissance style, I5W74, No. 3-8
    - Book illustration: L'Impromptu de Conde, I5W74, No. 9
  - Wood engravings, U.S., I5W78
    - Blank end-grain boxwood block, I5W78, No. 1
    - Wood engraving preparation, I5W78, No. 2-4
    - Adams, Tate, I5W78 A32, No. 1-11
    - Berkeley Albion Press mark, I5W78 C2, No. 1
    - Cheney, Sheldon, I5W78 C3, No. 1-9
    - [Hopson, William Fowler], I5W78 H6, No. 1
    - Merrymount Press Collection, I5W78 M38
    - Nahl, Charles Christian, I5W78 N3, No. 1
    - San Francisco Call artists, I5W78 S26, No. 1-3
  - Wood engravings, country unknown, I5W80
    - Hart Collection, I5W80 H37, No. 1-40
  - Zinc etchings, U.S., I5Z4
    - Hagedorn, Edward, I5Z4 H24, No. 1-2
  - Zinc engravings, U.S., I5Z6
    - Trial engraving on photoengraver's plate, I5Z6, No. 1
- Design, Decoration and Illustration: Electrotyping and Stereotyping, I52
  Of the two kinds of plates developed during the 19th century for the reproduction of illustrations and printed matter, the stereotype is the older. It is cast in type metal from a matrix, or mold, of plaster of Paris or paper pulp. Two examples of such matrices, or flongs, were intended for newspaper publication, the most common use of stereotyping. There is also a group of stereotypes of wood engravings from the estate of James D. Hart, who purchased them in Mexico City, apparently for his own use. Electrotype plates are made from wax molds on which a metal coating has been deposited by an electroplating process. Twelve plates in the collection were made for the four-color printing of a picture of the Tiffany window placed in the American Typefounders Company Library and Museum I 1931 to honor John Henry Nash. A great number of the electrotyped plates came in the Bianchi gift from the Merrymount Press. The best known designs that have been identified, by no means the majority, are by Cleland, Horne, and Ruzicka.
  - Electrotyping: procedural materials, I52E4
    - Foundry photoengraving: "Micro-metal" (zinc), I52E4, No. 1a
    - Bakelite mold for color process printing: yellow, I52E4, No. 1b
    - Foundry photoengraving: with removeable sections for two colors, I52E4, No. 2
    - Bakelite mold for color process printing: blue, I52E4, No. 3a
    - Bakelite mold for color process printing: red, I52E4, No. 3b
  - Electrotypes, I52E5
    - Berkeley Albion Press mark, I52E5, No. 1
    - Sheldon and Maud Cheney bookplate, I52E5, No. 2
    - Merrymount Press Collection, I52E5 M38
    - Halftone plates: Tiffany windows honoring J.H. Nash, I52E5 T4
  - Stereotypes, I52P68
    - Halftone photoengravings with matrices (flongs) for newspaper portrait of unidentified man, I52P683
    - Halftone plate cast from matrix (flong) for newspaper portrait of leaders of California Republican Party in 1906, I52P684
    - Stereotypes of wood engravings, I52P685
    - Hart Collection, I52P685 H37, No. 1-7
- Design, Decoration, and Illustration: Photographic Processes, I53
  In halftone photoengravings, regularly spaced dots of varying size reproduce grays, blacks, and color gradations. Several metals may be used, e.g. copper for the photoengravings of Diego Rivera’s portrait of Peter Stackpole, and for the four-color printing of bird paintings by the naturalist Andrew Jack Grayson; magnesium for the portrait of the pioneer printed Charles Murdock of San Francisco; zinc for Robert Louis Stevenson’s wood engraving “Lord Nelson and the Tar”, for drawings by the balletomane Paget-Fredericks, and for the drawings Victor Anderson did for booklets printed by James D. Hart as Christmas greetings.
  The 19th century brought the invention of lithography, the process of printing from smooth, porous limestones, like those entered as part of the binding collection because they were used by binders as paring stones. A much smaller limestone came with the tools of the 20th century lithographer George Raymond Noonan and still bears the print of the last image reproduced on it. Plates for photo-offset lithography include a stage set by Henry May for Andrew Imbrie’s opera Three Against Christmas. They could be attached to a cylinder, transferred to a blanket cylinder, and thence to the printing paper carried on an impression cylinder.
  - Brass photoengravings, I53B5
    - Advertising plates for Kaiser Company, I53B5, No. 1-2
  - Copper photoengravings, I53C6
    - Halftone portrait: Joseph Winfred Spenceley, I53C6, No. 1
    - Halftone portrait: William Fowler Hopson, I53C6, No. 2
    - Halftone manuscript page: Obregon's History of the 16th Century Explorations...,ed. by G.P. Hammond & A. Rey. Los Angeles: Wetzel, 1928, I53C6, No. 3
    - Halftones for four-color process printing of bird paintings by Andrew Jackson Grayson, I53C6 G7, No. 1-60
    - Norman H. Strouse, Silverado Press Bookplates, by W. O. Holt, I53C6 H4, No. 1-2
    - Merritt, Warren Chase, I53C6 M4, No. 1-8
    - Portrait of Peter Stackpole by Diego Rivera, I53C6 P6, No. 1
    - Norman H. Strouse, Silverado Press mark, by Leo Wyatt, I53C6 W8, No. 1-3
  - Magnesium photoengravings, I53M68
    - Blank plate, I53M68, No. 1
    - Halftone illustrations: Harding, George. Charles A. Murdock. (Berkeley: Tamalpais Press, 1973), I53M68 M8, No. 1-7
    - Line and halftone illustration: Home and Vegetable Garden (U.C. Agricultural Extension Service Circular No. 26), I53M68 T46, No. 1
  - Photographic negatives, I53N64
    - Negative for photoengraving or photo-offset plate, I53N64, No. 1
  - Photogravure, I53P54
    - Plate: Rouget de Lisle singing "La Marseillaise", I53P54, No. 1
  - Stone Lithography, I53P55
    - Transfer stone, I53P55, No. 1
    - Tools, I53P55, No. 2-25
  - Zincography, I53P56
    - Lithographic plate, I53P56, No. 1
  - Photo-offset lithography (planography), I53P57
    - Photo-offset plate: railroad collision, I53P57, No. 1
    - Negative and plate of stage set designed by Henry May, I53P57 M2, No. 1-2
  - Zinc photoengravings, I53Z4
    - Halftone: cuneiform tablet (BART A5C53 No. 1), I53Z4, No. 1
    - In line: map, Northwestern New Spain, 1583, I53Z4, No. 2
    - Halftone: Portrait of Robert Frost, I53Z4, No. 3
    - 1952-76 In line: drawings by Victor R. Anderson, I53Z4 A52
    - In line: from proof to linocut by Rick Barton, I53Z4 B2, No. 1
    - In line: bookplates designed by Sheldon Cheney, I53Z4 C3, No. 1-10
    - In line: Crown Zellerbach Building, I53Z4 C4, No. 1
    - In line: endpapers designed by Robert Eustachy, I53Z4 E8, No. 1
    - In line: Stockton Boyhood drawings by C.E. Grunsky, I53Z4 G86, No. 1-12
    - In line: Hart Collection, I53Z4 H37, No. 1-2
    - In line: drawings by Lloyd Hoff, I53Z4 H62, No. 1 and 1942-51
    - In line: Abe Martin caricatures by Frank McKinney Hubbard, I53Z4 H82, No. 1-2
    - In line: portrait of William F. Knowland, I53Z4 K5, No. 1
    - In line: drawings by Lois Lenski, I53Z4 L35, No. 1-3
    - In line: pages from The Lark (with negative), I53Z4 M8, No. 1-2
    - Merrymount Press Collection, I53Z4 M38
    - In line: John Henry Nash initials, I53Z4 N27, No. 1
    - Halftone: Aerial view of Yosemite Valley, I53Z4 035
    - In line: drawings by Joseph Paget-Fredricks, I53Z4 P24 No. 1-3
    - In line: Christmas cards by Ernest C. Peixotto, I53Z4 P37, No. 1-4
    - In line: Platen Press mark (Ted Freedman), I53Z4 P52, No. 1-3
    - In line: traditional Spanish images, I53Z4 S3, No. 1-6
    - In line: "Lord Nelson and the Tar" by R.L. Stevenson, I53Z4 S6, No. 1
    - In line: Aundo Press marks by WIlliam Gray Purcell and Fredrick Folger Thomas, Jr. (No. 11 Amateur Journals of the Past logo), I53Z4 T5, No. 1-11
    - In line: United Nations emblem, I53Z4 U6, No. 1
    - White Labor League Boot & Shoe Makers logo, I53Z4 W44, No. 1
- Design, Decoration and Illustration: Photochemical processes, I54
  Photopolymer printing plates are used to print magazines and books. The plate contains polymeric material that is ultraviolet photosensitive and produces an image when exposed to light. A specimen of photopolymer printing plates is the “Scanagraph” plate of a locomotive and freight cars on a trestle from The Los Gatos Times-Observer.
  - Photopolymer printing plates for relief printing, I54P52
    - "Scanagraph" plate: 80-line screen for newspaper illustration, I54P52, No. 1
- Design, Decoration, and Illustration: Prints, Proofs and Drawings, I55
  This section contains a few drawings, notably Henry Evans’ press mark, drawn by Mel Fowler, and Henry May’s pen and ink sketch of the stage set for Three Against Christmas. Among many proofs are a full set of trial ink proofs showing the four-color process printing of Robert Quick’s Portfolio of Fish (San Francisco: Henry Evans, 1959) and photo-offset progressive proofs of the photograph Jack Cannon took for the dust jack of Ruth Newhall’s book The Enchanted Palace (Berkeley: Howell North, 1967).
  - Copper Engravings, I55C6 G7
    - Four color proof: copper halftone photoengraving of a bird watercolor by Andrew Jackson Grayson, I55C6 G7, No. 1
  - [Paste-up], I55D7 A7
    - Paste-up combining printed name "Alcuin Press" and original drawing of press mark of Frederick Folger Thomas, Jr., I55D7 A7, No. 1
  - [Drawing], I55D7 F7
    - Drawing of press mark for Henry Evan's Peregrine Press by Mel Fowler, 155D7 F7, No. 1
  - [Letterpress], I55L2 C3
    - Bookplate designed by Sheldon Cheney and printed from zinc photoengraving in BART collection, I55L2 G3, No. 1
  - [Letterpress], I55L2 G7
    - Progressive ink proofs: four-color halftone of printing of bird watercolor by Andrew Jackson Grayson, I55L2 G7, No. 1-8
  - [Proof], I55L2 H37
    - Proof: routes to home of J.D. Hart, I55L2 H37, No. 1
  - [Photo-offset proofs], I55 P37
    - Photo-offset proofs: dust jacket for San Francisco's Enchanted Palace, I55 P37, No. 1-7
  - [Photo-offset proofs], I55 P57
    - Photo-offset proofs: stage sets by Henry May, I55 P57, No. 1-2
  - [Proof: Orientalia], I55W67
    - Proof: Tibetan prayer board, I55W67, No. 1
  - [Proofs: Orientalia], I55W67 M2
    - woodcut by Masanobu, 1693-1798. Proof on Japanese paper of woodcut of representation of Tenjin with pine and plus, I55W67 M2, No. 1
    - woodcut by Masanobu, 1693-1798. Proof on Japanese paper of woodcut, I55W67 M2, No. 2
  - [Proofs: Orientalia], I55W67 S4
    - Proof: woodcut by Shigemasa, I55W67 S4, No. 1
  - [Proof], I55W68
    - Proof: "angel" woodcut by anonymous artist, I55W68, No. 1
  - [Drawings and trial ink proofs], I55W68 Q4
    - Drawings and trial ink proofs: four-color printing of linocuts by Robert Quick, I55W68 Q4, No. 1-42
  - [Proof], I55W68 R84
    - Proof: bookplate by Rudolph Ruzicka, I55W68 R84, No. 1
  - [Proofs], I55W68 S3
    - Proofs: traditional Spanish images, I55W68 S3, No. 1-6
  - [Proofs], I55W73 C22
    - Proofs: wood engravings by Robert Catterson-Smith for Ashendene Dante, I55W73 C22, No. 3, 4, 13, 26, 28, 33, 35, 37, 38, 40, A1-A43
  - [Proofs], I55W73 G43
    - Proofs: wood engravings by C.M. Gere for Ashendene St. Francis, Morte Darthur, I55W73 G43, No. 1-31, 33
  - [Proof], I55W78 N3
    - Proof: wood engraving by Charles Christian Nahl, I55W78 N3, No. 1
  - [Proof], I55W78 S26
    - Proof: wood engraving for San Francisco Call masthead, I55W78 S26, No. 1
- Paper-making and Trade, Handmade Paper, and Machine-Made Paper, P2; ca. 1360 items
  The process of papermaking may be demonstrated with equipment originally acquired for the School of Library and Information Science by Roger Levenson. While an instructor in printing, he studied the craft of papermaking in order to demonstrate its main principles and give students a hands-on experience. When the School was disbanded the BART collection acquired the personal manual Levenson developed and a small electric-powered Hollander beater.
  Among earlier acquisitions are examples of two objects crucial to paper production: the mold and the deckle. The mold is a shallow, wooden frame with a wire-screen bottom, finely meshed to produce wove paper (in which gauze-like marks may be visible), or more coarsely meshed to produce laid paper (think, vertical chain lines are visible when the paper is held against the light). Either kind of screen may bear a projecting design, which will leave a watermark in the paper. Two laid-paper molds from the print shop of John Henry Nash carry his watermark; only one has its deckle, a wooden frame that fits over the mold to contain the pulp when the mold is dipped into the vat.
  From the commercial manufacture of paper there are several wove screens (illustrating a variety of watermark techniques) cut from the dandy roll (a cylinder) of Fourdrinier paper-making machine, the modern descendent of the first paper-making machine built in England in 1810 by Henry Fourdrinier.